Avleen Kaur

Ph.D. Mathematics Student

420 Machray Hall, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg MB, R3T 2N2, Canada

📞 +1 (204) 990-2981 | 🖂 kaura349@myumanitoba.ca | 🏕 avleenk2312.github.io | 🖸 avleenk2312 | in avleen-kaur-math | Citizenship: Canadian

Summary _

My research interests are linear algebra, numerical analysis, and partial differential equations. The core of my PhD thesis is devising and analyzing space-time spectral method for partial differential equations, with a special focus on the Stokes problem. While working on estimating condition number for matrices, the problem of deriving a non-trivial lower bound for the minimum eigenvalue of a SPD matrix expressed as a sum of two PSD matrices captured my interest. This problem further lead to new lower bounds for some block matrices. A future project includes developing a fast solver for linear systems arising from space-time spectral methods.

In addition to learning mathematics, my other passion is teaching mathematics at various levels. I have taught a second year engineering mathematical analysis course in Winter 2021 at the University of Manitoba, where I have also worked as a teaching assistant for various courses for the past six years. During this time, I also conducted several workshops for preparing students for university level mathematics, and nursing examination. And, I tutor students registered with special education programs. I love volunteering for teaching mathematics to elementary school students in Manitoba. I occasionally give free Indian classical music lessons at Gurdwara Nanaksar, Winnipeg.

Education

Ph.D. Mathematics

University of Manitoba Sept. 2017-PRESENT

Supervisor: Dr. Shaun LuiCurrent GPA: 4.33/4.5

M.Sc. Mathematics

University of Manitoba Sept. 2015-Aug. 2017

• Supervisors: Dr. Craig Cowan, Dr. Shaun Lui

- Thesis Title: The Eigenvalue Problem of the Uzawa Pressure Operator [PDF]
- GPA: 4.40/4.5

M.Sc. Mathematics and Scientific Computing

MOTILAL NEHRU NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY ALLAHABAD

July 2013-May 2015

- GOLD MEDALIST
- Supervisor: Dr. Gorakh Nath
- Thesis Title: Series Solution of Shock Wave Problems
- GPA: 9.76/10

B.Sc. Computer Science

GURU NANAK DEV UNIVERSITY, AMRITSAR PB, INDIA

June 2010-June 2013

University Merit Student

Publications

IN PREPARATION

- 1. Space-time ultraspherical spectral methods for linear PDEs. Avleen Kaur, S.H.Lui.
- 2. A space-time spectral method for the Stokes problem. Avleen Kaur, S.H.Lui.
- 3. New lower bounds on the minimum singular value of a matrix Avleen Kaur, S.H.Lui.

PUBLISHED

1. On the blast wave propagation and structure in a rotational axisymmetric perfect gas.

Avleen Kaur, Gorakh Nath, Satish Chaurasiya.

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, India Section A: Physical Sciences. (2021)

Conferences and Talks _

INVITED TALKS

International Conference on Spectral and Higher Order Methods (ICOSAHOM)
 Vienna, Austria, July 2020 2021, Held Online due to COVID-19.

CONTRIBUTED TALKS

- Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics Annual Meeting (SIAM-AN21) Virtual Conference, July 2021.
- Canadian Applied and Industrial Mathematics Society Annual Meeting (CAIMS) Waterloo, ON, Held Online due to COVID-19, June 2021.
- Connecting Women in Mathematics Across Canada (CWiMAC) STUDENT/POST DOCTORAL PRESENTATION PRIZE Virtual Conference, June 2021.
- Western Canada Linear Algebra Meeting (WCLAM)

 Brandon, MB, Held Online due to COVID-19, May 2021.
- SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra (SIAM-LA21) Virtual Conference, May 2021.
- Canadian Mathematical Society (CMS-STUDC Research) Vancouver BC, December 2018.

WORKSHOP PARTICIPATION

- PIMS Math^Industry Workshop
 - Online, August 2021.
 - Personal Webpage.
 - Certificate of participation and description of Workshop [PDF].
 - Seven courses and two weeks internship with Aerium Analytics.
 - Team Project: Al for Road Surface Scanning (report under revision), see **webpage**.
- AMS Winter School
- CMS Mini Course: Control of Partial Differential Equations CMS Winter Meeting, Toronto ON, December 2019.
- PIMS CRG Summer School: Neural Networks and Deep Learning Simon Fraser University, Burnaby BC, July 2019.
- NPDE-TCA Advanced Level Training Program 2014
 IISER Thiruvananthapuram, Kerala, India, May-June 2014.
- Summer Visiting Student Programme 2014

 IISER Thiruvananthapuram, Kerala, India, May-July 2014.
- UGC Basic Scientific Research Scheme 2013 ACFA Jalandhar PB, India, January-April 2013.

Honors & Awards _____

PIMS, Canada	PIMS Intern Stipend	2021
CWiMAC, Canada	Student/Post Doctoral Presentation Prize	2021
University of Manitoba	Fellowship for Education Purposes by Faculty of Science	2020
University of Manitoba	Graduate Award for Excellence in Mathematics	2018
University of Manitoba	University of Manitoba Graduate Fellowship	2018-2021
University of Manitoba	Dr. Murray Gordon Bell Graduate Student Award	2017
University of Manitoba	Second Prize for Graduate Seminar	2016
MNNIT Allahabad	Gold Medal in Master of Science	2015
IISER Thiruvananthapuram	Summer Visiting Student Stipend	2014
GNDU Amritsar	Merit Student in Bachelor of Science	2013
ACFA Jalandhar	Second Prize for Paper Presentation	2013
GNDU Amritsar	UGC Basic Scientific Research Award	2012

Teaching

EXPERIENCE

Instructor Winnipeq, MB

UNIVERSITY OF MANITOBA

• MATH 2132-Engineering Mathematical Analysis 2- Winter 2021.

- · Class of 203 students.
- Letter of Performance Evaluation [PDF]

Teaching Assistant Winnipeg, MB

University of Manitoba

- Nominated for Faculty of Science Award for Excellence in Teaching Assistance.
- First year courses include:
 - Applied Finite Mathematics
 - Calculus I
 - Elementary Discrete Mathematics
 - Mathematics in Art
 - Techniques of Classical and Linear Algebra
 - Vector Geometry and Linear Algebra
- · Second year courses include:
 - Introduction to Analysis
 - Linear Algebra 2
 - Mathematical Modelling
 - Multi-variable Calculus
 - Mathematics for Data Science
 - Numerical Analysis I
- Math Help Centre, where students of all first and second year courses come to ask questions.

Graduate Student Research Mentor

Winnipeg, MB Jan. 2022 - April 2022

Jan. 2021 - April 2021

Sept. 2015 - PRESENT

Manitoba experimental Mathematics Laboratory

• Project: Simulation of fluid flow inside a disk.

Tutor for Pathway to Indigenous Nursing Education

Winnipeg, MB

University of Manitoba

• This is a program designed for aboriginal students studying nursing at the University of Manitoba.

Instructor for JUMP Math Workshop

Winnipeg, MB

PIMS-University of Manitoba

Sept. 2020

Sept. 2021 - PRESENT

A four-day online workshop for preparing students for the Applied Finite Mathematics course at the University of Manitoba.

Instructor for Math Boot Camp

Winnipeg, MB

University of Manitoba

Aug. 2020

• A series of six online tutorials sessions for teaching Pre-Calculus to the University of Manitoba students.

Instructor for Saturday Workshop Series

Winnipeg, MB

University of Manitoba

Sept. 2019, Jan. 2020, Sept. 2020

• A series of three workshops designed to prepare students for university-level Mathematics.

Tutor for Aboriginal Nursing Cohort Initiative

*Winnipeg, MB*Sept. 2020 - Dec. 2020

University of Manitoba

Scpt. 2020 - Di

• This is a program designed for aboriginal students studying nursing at the University of Manitoba.

Tutor for Access and Aboriginal Focus Programs

Sept. 2019 - Dec. 2020

University of Manitoba

• This is a program designed for aboriginal students or for students needing additional support. This job requires to give individual attention to each student and reporting their progress to the instructor.

Teaching Assistant for Math Boot Camp

Winnipeg, MB

Winnipeg, MB

University of Manitoba

2016-2017

· A workshop for teaching Pre-Calculus to the University students.

DEVELOPMENT

Graduate Teaching Program

Winnipeg, MB

THE CENTRE FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF TEACHING AND LEARNING, UNIVERSITY OF MANITOBA

May 2021-PRESENT

Accredited through SEDA, a professional association in the United Kingdom that promotes innovation and good practices in higher education.

· For more information, see GTP.

Graduate Student Teacher Training

Winnipeg, MB

2016

UNIVERSITY OF MANITOBAUnder Dr. Donald Trim.

• A workshop with award-winning educator on teaching techniques which included peer and mentor feedback on a teaching presentation.

Outreach

PIMS-Math Mania PIMS Manitoha

VOLUNTEER 2018 - PRESENT

· A math education outreach programme for children, involving visits to local schools and to schools on remote First Nation reserves.

Science Rendezvous University of Manitoba

BOOTH CAPTAIN, VOLUNTEER

2020, 2019

• A hands-on science festival to encourage public engagement with science.

Committee of Graduate Students for Scientific Interdisciplinary Talks (CoGSIT)

University of Manitoba

COMMITTEE MEMBER

Feb. 2019 - PRESENT

• The work consists of inviting world-renowned scientists and organizing their talks.

Math Kangaroo Contest University of Manitoba

VOLUNTEER

2019

· Helped in organizing the event.

Mathematics Headship Search Committee

University of Manitoba

COMMITTEE MEMBER

• A committee for hiring the head of the Department of Mathematics.

Department of Mathematics MNNIT Allahabad

MASTER'S STUDENTS' REPRESENTATIVE

2014-2015

• Participated in several conferences.

· Organized departmental events.

• Communicated with Master's student for all official activities.

Indian Classical Music Training

Gurdwara Nanaksar, Winnipeg

VOLUNTEER TEACHER

2019

• As a part of free summer school for children at the Gurdwara Nanaksar.

Relevant Skills _____

C, C++, Julia, HTML, LTFX, Machine Learning, MATLAB, PL/SQL, Python, R, SQL. Languages Anaconda, Atom, Mathematica, Microsoft Softwares, RStudio, Octave. **Software**

Noteworthy High-Performance Computing (HPC) Programmer: an active user of Westgrid and the supercomputer Grex.

Extra-Curricular Classical Indian music singer and instrument player (Harmonium), Gym enthusiast, Runner

References

· Dr. S.H. Lui

Professor, Mathematics University of Manitoba Shaun.Lui@umanitoba.ca

· Dr. Craig Cowan

Associate Professor, Mathematics University of Manitoba Craig.Cowan@umanitoba.ca

· Dr. Darja Barr

Instructor, Mathematics University of Manitoba Darja.Barr@umanitoba.ca